What were the largest corporations of
ancient Rome?
It's an interesting question to ponder
and one which raises yet more questions.
Did Rome even have corporations? What
were its largest industries? Who ran
these enterprises?
If you want to win up to $500 in BassPro
gift cards, stay tuned. In this video,
we shall seek to provide answers by
having a look at the overall economic
landscape of antiquity and seeing how
people within it worked together to
build their own business empires.
From the familiar households that ran
small businesses or accumulated massive
estates to the clientele and networks
that allowed for vertical and horizontal
growth within markets, the societies
which pulled wealth to fund risky
ventures like maritime expeditions, the
professional guilds that coordinated to
regulate and self- advocate for their
industry, and the Publicani private
contractors who competed to take on many
of the government's essential functions
like tax farming or infrastructure
maintenance.
In these reviews, we pay special
attention to how these various
enterprises were organized and how they
were viewed within the framework of
Rome's legal system.
It's a fascinating aspect of the past
that contains surprisingly modern
features like insurance schemes, shared
trading, limited liability principles,
and more. Unfortunately, it all too
often gets overlooked in favor of more
flashy topics like wars and battles.
But these were actually far off matters
for most common people. So today, let's
take a look at the real lived experience
of the everyday person to see what the
business world was like in ancient Rome.
Today's video was brought to you by our
sponsor, Metal Hunter. It's a fast-paced
shooting game where you fight across
different war zones to test your
precision, timing, and skill for
intercepting targets across land, air,
and sea. You'll be deploying across nine
launch locations from across the eras
where you man the guns of a flack
battery, an artillery imp placement, or
a sniper nest. As you play, unlocking
locations also unlocks you spins for
winning prizes on the mhch challenge.com
site with a $30,000 prize pool in
BassPro gift cards.
The Metal Hunter gameplay sees you
compete with other players in three-wave
PvP duels. No auto aim, just skill. As a
veteran marksman, you'll learn to make
the optimal choice when it comes to your
rifle and your ammunition to have the
most optimized shot on target. Along the
way, you can build up your haven,
upgrade your weapons, collect gunner
cards, and climb the rankings. So,
download the game to get started and use
my gift code Invicta for an exclusive
welcome package. Remember to unlock
arenas to unlock spins for a chance to
win a part of the $30,000 prize pool.
And let me know in the comments below
what you've won. In my case, I was lucky
enough to win this $25 gift card on the
first shot. So, set your sights and good
luck.
Just as today the economic world of
antiquity was a vibrant one with many
players small and large interacting
across a dynamic ecosystem.
While our main focus in this video will
be the largest players in the scene, it
will be useful to start by exploring the
environment from which they merged.
The first point to make is that the
world of antiquity was largely an
agrarian one. While cities were
certainly important, especially when it
comes to getting their names into the
history books, most of the population
lived in rural environments, working
agricultural jobs. This primarily meant
farming plots of land and hurting
livestock. But these are broad terms and
one must imagine a huge amount of
specialization which varied from region
to region based on the available natural
resources. For instance, a hilly upland
area might turn to sheep. A volcanic
coastal area to wine. A forested area
would develop hunting and logging. A
mineral-rich area would have quaries and
mines and so on.
But outside of what could immediately be
consumed, all these raw materials were
of limited value in and of themselves.
Indeed, they would have to be
transported for storage, processing, and
exchange. Where such goods accumulated,
so too did people. Thus, the vast
agrarian landscape would be dotted with
population centers of various sizes.
Each of these nodes was connected to one
another through a logistics network of
roads, rivers, and seas. Broadly
speaking, such hubs imported the raw
goods of their surroundings, freeing up
their people to take on more specialized
roles. In this way, did wealth,
investment, and expertise develop, which
led to the growth of villages, towns,
and cities. Urban economies were thus of
a different nature than their rural
counterparts. Here, vibrant markets
traded in goods originating from far and
wide which could be tapped into by a
diverse working class of crafts people,
artisans, and merchants. Specialized
industries included construction,
pottery manufacturing, brickmaking, and
textiles to name just a few. Layered
over it all would naturally be the legal
and administrative bureaucracies
required to manage the population and
its surrounding lands.
Now that we've briefly laid out this
economic environment, we can consider
how rural and urban people banded
together to take on the collective
action of business.
On the smallest end of the spectrum
would be the household or familia. Here
a husband, wife, their children,
extended relatives, servants, and slaves
would form a hierarchical community
under the absolute authority of the
senior male or potterfamil.
It was a well-established social
structure which was enforced by legal
principles.
These enshrined the rights of the
paraphernalius to own property in the
name of the family, collect the earnings
of his dependents, and ultimately wield
the power of life and death over them.
When it came to business affairs, the
Potter Familas had final say. Actions
taken on his behalf required
authorization, and there was a concept
of an agent or instor who would be
appointed to officially act as their
surrogate. Importantly, liability for
the actions of an agent flowed back to
the master. So long, of course, as they
had not gone rogue, a tricky point of
contention that was often argued in
court when things went sour.
With this concept of the household-sized
enterprise in mind, we can go through
what it looked like across the social
spectrum, rich and poor, rural and
urban.
Poor rural families likely resided in a
small home on a pl of land which they
either owned as free landholders or
perhaps one which they rented as
tenants.
From here they would go about the
business of the land. Some might travel
further a field, acting as hired hands
for larger plots or for intensive
seasonal work.
Poor urban families, meanwhile, were
likely to reside in the cramped
multi-story apartments known as the
Ensuli. There was little business to be
had here, and so work likely meant
descending into the city as a laborer in
one of the many businesses. Some
families might even rent or own a stall
in a public space or the ground floor of
the apartment from which they could
operate their own small enterprise.
Wealthier families would have been able
to manage more substantial affairs. In
rural areas, this would have meant
owning large estates. Their operations
were beyond the scope of what a family
could work on its own and would have
thus included many free or enslaved
workers. And while the powderfamil may
have been an engaged landlord, daily
operations typically fell to a
management team of stewards and foremen
who presided over the labor force.
Altogether, such large rural estates
could easily have headcounts in the
dozens or hundreds.
Rich urban households, meanwhile, would
have been based around a domos. This was
a large private home built around a
central courtyard with room for private
dwellings and living spaces in the back
in addition to public-f facing business
areas in the front. The latter of these
could be used to run the family store or
might be rented out as commercial space.
Overall, these homes were not as
sprawling and well staffed as their
rural counterparts, but nonetheless
hosted sizable families which might rely
on dozens of servants and slaves.
At the highest levels of society would
have been the wealthiest families of
Rome, the patricians who held the senior
offices of government and filled the
Senate. Though as an aside, we should
note that rich plebbeans would later
ascend to this upper echelon as the old
class distinctions grew increasingly
blurred by the late republic. That
aside, all men of this rank enjoyed
sprawling mansions and villas of
extraordinary extravagance. In addition,
they likely owned sizable tracks of real
estate across both the rural and urban
landscape for personal use and for
renting. Of particular note were the
Lafundia, massive agricultural estates
in the hands of the rich, often staffed
by slaves and cheap labor, which
increasingly dominated their neighbors.
Understandably, the power of such elites
became a concern, certainly among the
poor, but more importantly among their
rich peers with whom they competed. Thus
over the years there reformed various
social and legal curbs on the senatorial
class.
On a social level the expectation was
that senators were beyond the work of
the commoners. This meant absolutely no
manual labor and an avoidance of many
professions. Instead they were to make
their money as landlords and to turn
their minds to higher pursuits. Cicero
describes it as follows. quote, "But the
professions in which a higher degree of
intelligence is required or from which
no small benefit to society is derived,
medicine and architecture, for example,
and teaching, these are proper for those
whose social position they become."
On the legal front, laws seem to have
been put in place to codify these
restraints. The Lex Claudia of 218 BC,
for example, prohibited senators and
their sons from owning maritime vessels
with a capacity greater than 340.
The logic behind this cutoff seems to be
that this amount could reasonably be
expected to service their regular
affairs. However, anything more strayed
into the realm of actual trade, which
was the purview of merchants.
Enforcement of all this, meanwhile,
would largely be done by the sensors.
These were powerful magistrates elected
every 5 years for an 18-month term.
During this period, their main job was
to count citizens and assess their
properties. Critically, they were also
meant to update the official senatorial
roles. If an audit found a senator had
insufficient or illegal financials, then
they could be removed from the list.
Particularly egregious behavior might
even result in the issuing of a not
sensoria or mark of infamy, which could
strip them of voting rights or social
status.
These mechanisms seem to have had some
effect. However, there were many ways to
bend or bypass the rules. Often this
meant doing business through proxies
outside of one's immediate family. This
will now get us into the next tier of
collective commercial action.
Besides the familia, Roman society was
also organized along a broader social
system of clientella.
Essentially, this was a semiformal
network linking a powerful patron to
their lesser clients. Scholars argue to
what extent these relationships were
inherited and obligatory,
but regardless, they served an important
function in the ancient world. The
concept basically boils down to an
expectation that the clients supported
the endeavors of their patron in
exchange for favors and services.
For instance, a patron may call upon
their clients to support their political
campaign, to work a job, to manage an
enterprise, to rough up the competition,
or to simply walk alongside them as an
entourage meant to display their power.
In exchange, these clients would expect
to receive foods, funds, protection, and
other privileges.
Such clientella proved particularly
important for commercial activity.
Clients, for instance, could seek a loan
from their patron, ask them for legal
services, or make introductions and
network. Most importantly, a client who
proved their loyalty and competence to a
patron would be rewarded with trust.
This was an all-important social
currency which undergured nearly every
interaction at a time when society
otherwise lacked the robust modern
bureaucracies and communications which
maintained the rules of the road in our
own world. With trust, a patron could
vouch for you to be who you said you
were to be of good standing and to honor
an agreement.
Breaking this trust reflected poorly on
a patron who would in turn seek to
punish you. Thus we have a fairly robust
system of checks and balances which
enabled the functioning of a complex
economy.
Now to the question of the sorts of
businesses that might be built upon
these clientella. Well, they came in all
shapes and sizes. After all, client
networks could help a business grow its
operations both horizontally and
vertically. The former might mean using
clients to staff and manage a large
textile business. The latter might mean
leveraging clients who could supply the
raw materials or distribute the final
products.
Roman law seems to have recognized these
sorts of business arrangements,
especially with regards to legal
disputes. For instance, it seems that
clients could absorb the risk of some
business endeavors, shielding their
patron with an ancient version of
limited liability.
This practice also seems to have existed
in the form of slave managers who could
be installed at the head of some
business to do what their boss demanded,
but to take the fall if necessary.
In this way, client networks proved
extremely useful and could get quite
extensive, especially among the most
powerful Romans. For example, it seems
that entire cities might find themselves
under the patronage of a particular
politician. In extreme cases, even
entire regions or kingdoms could lash
themselves to a powerful Roman patron.
However, we must caution that at these
levels, the lines get blurred between
the affairs of individuals and the
affairs of government. Thus, it can be
unfair to lump together such loose
clientele networks and treat them as
some sort of mega corporation. In
reality, it was far more informal than
that. However, there were other
institutions that do get us closer to
such a concept. This now gets us into
the topic of the collegia and the
publicani.
Colleia were groups that emerged as
people of a similar profession began to
formalize their associations.
This sort of activity is an expected
byproduct of our nature as a social
species and can be seen emerging across
the ancient world. In Rome, it seems
that the earliest evidence of such trade
groups could be traced back to the reign
of King Numa, whom Plutarch claims quote
organized the distribution of the people
into groups according to their trades or
arts into musicians, goldsmiths,
carpenters, dyers, leather workers,
curers, brazers, and potters. The
remaining trades he grouped together and
made one body out of all who belong to
them. He also appointed social
gatherings and public assemblies and
rights of worship befitting each body.
We can imagine that such groups would
have continued to exist over the years
as important socioeconomic entities.
Likely this manifested in concentrated
zones within towns where similar
professions elomerated into something
like a metalworking district or a
jewelry district. In other places like
the melting pot of Alexandria, these
concentrations might form around
particular cultural communities.
But such groupings could also happen in
a more dynamic mobile way as seems to
have occurred with construction. Here,
large bands of laborers were reported to
rove across towns and regions in search
of a big job to work for a few months or
years. Such activities may have been
coordinated by some sort of leadership
structure in the same way that mercenary
or auxiliary companies had their
captains. Unfortunately, we have no
records to substantiate the speculation.
We do, however, have a better
understanding of the more structured
groups that chose to form Kia.
These were roughly the equivalent of
guilds, though with a more social focus
than a purely economic one. They
appeared across the Roman world in a
myriad of forms which we lack the
details to fully understand. Broadly
speaking though, it seems that they were
associations formed around either
professional or religious lines. In
either case, it seems that members would
pull resources and appoint a management
team which could operate out of some
central headquarters.
Funds typically came from fees,
membership dues, donations, and wills.
The collegia in return would represent
the member's economic interest, set
trade standards, enforce rules, settle
disputes, host banquetss, arrange
funerals, and provide other benefits.
For a closer look at the collegia, we
can turn to the Roman port city of
Austia, which had an incredible number
of such groups. This included a guild
for the ship builders, the cockers, the
rope makers, the boat guides, the
fairmen, the dock hands, the warehouse
guards, the grain measures, the rescue
divers, the fishermen, the bankers, the
charioteers, and more. Each had its own
skola or headquarters building on the
main road. Some were quite extensive
with their own banquet halls, gardens,
and even bathous.
As for their internal workings, it seems
that the Kia were managed by a board of
elected members. At its head was the
Quincodonalis who presided for 5 years.
It was a powerful position with great
social status whose title appears to
have been carried by the holder even
after they left office. Besides them
were a pair of castori or treasurers who
manage incoming and outgoing funds.
Other managers or magistry carried out
the various needs of the group.
In addition to this main board would be
the collegiia's patrons. These were
wealthy individuals like city
councilmen, noble women, senators or
even emperors who found their interests
aligned with the profession of a guild
and threw their weight behind it in
exchange for some political or economic
backing. In this way, some powerful
members could actually serve as patrons
to multiple guilds. As you can imagine,
this could lead to a truly sprawling
network of influence.
The power of such colleia grew over the
years, especially in the late republic
as the equestrian class came to compete
financially with the patricians of old.
Understandably, their wealth and
collective action could prove
threatening to the powers that be.
Emperor Trajan says as much when
responding to plenty about a request to
set up a special fire brigade in Nikico
Media. Quote, "We should remember that
your province and especially those
cities have been troubled by factions of
this sort. Whatever name we give to
them, for whatever purpose, men who have
been brought together for the same
purpose will quickly become political
clubs.
Thus, it was that laws were enacted to
limit the size or outright ban the
existence of the collegia. Restrictions
were particularly ramped up in the
transition from republic to empire as
authority was centralized. However, once
things smoothed out, restrictions were
gradually eased and the collegia were
tentatively accepted as a necessary but
regulated institution.
A great example of this comes to us from
the 6th century digest of Justinian
which reads as follows. Quote,
"Partnerships, collegia and bodies of
this sort may not be formed by everybody
at will for this right is restricted by
statute. Senitus consulta and imperial
constitution.
In a few cases only are bodies of this
sort permitted. Those permitted to form
a corporate body consisting of a
collegium or partnership or specifically
one or the other of these have the right
on the pattern of the state to have
common property, a common treasury and
an attorney or syndic through whom, as
in a state, what should be transacted
and done in common is transacted and
done.
As can be seen in this passage, the
government was particularly wary of
concentrated power outside of its
control. Yet at the same time, Rome's
ancient bureaucracy was unable to do
everything itself. Thus, it had to
delegate many of its essential
functions.
This now gets us to the last major
topic, the societus publicanorum.
Publicani were private contractors
engaged in activities essential to the
state, namely tax collection, military
logistics, mine operation, and
infrastructure management. Their
emergence coincided with the Punic Wars
and Rome's rapid expansion across the
Mediterranean in the mid to late
republic.
The way this worked is that when the
government wished to outsource its
duties, a public auction was held for
the right to the contract over a given
period, usually for the 5 years of the
reigning sensors tenure. The various
publicani then submitted their bids for
the job. Upon review, the best bid won,
at least in theory. Palibius gives us
some details on how one might angle to
be awarded. Quote, "Some purchase the
contracts from the sensors themselves.
Others go partners with them while
others again give security for these
contracts or actually pledge their
property to the treasury for them.
Such contracts could be extremely
lucrative, especially when it came to
tax collection. Here, the government
would put a request for the amount of
money it estimated could be raised from
a particular area. The Publicani then
agreed to provide that amount or more
before going on to collect the funds
themselves with any extra money they
might raise going directly to their
profits.
As can be expected, this was a system
ripe for abuse as the private
contractors sought to squeeze the
provinces dry. This often led to a
blowback effect of tax evasion and
unrest, which in the long term led the
Roman government to reform or reclaim
some of these duties.
So, how did these groups operate?
As always, the answer is that it varied.
Publicane might be a small family-based
entity or could be large societies made
up of multiple members and their
dependents.
This diagram proves useful in proposing
an org chart for the latter case based
on surviving customs law records. As you
can see, there is an overall societ with
a recognized leader who serves as the
menps and seems to have been the one
named in the government's contract. They
likely worked out of a central
headquarters with its own staff and
treasury.
Beneath it are various societas which
are led by a partner or socios. Each had
its own area of focus with the staff
resources and subcontractors in place to
do its job. In this example, we have
several partners tasked with the on the
ground tax collecting while others
provide local facilities, put up assets
for contract security, and provide loan
services.
As with the Collegia and other
societies, this entire arrangement was
recognized in Roman law in that they had
the right to common property and common
treasury as in the manner of estate, yet
in court might be defended by an
individual. The law further addresses
limited liability when it recognizes the
concept that quote, "My partner's
partner is not my partner."
And lastly, we should mention that some
sources make note of joint ownership
arrangement where shares in the society
could be purchased for a cut of the
profits.
Putting it all together, it is tempting
to view this sort of society as an
ancient corporation. However, this is a
contentious topic of much debate.
Academics warn against drawing such
conclusions when we lack evidence that
the Romans granted societies the well-
definfined rights of distinct personage
and limited liability characteristic of
modern corporations. There's also the
apparent fact that not all societies
were organized in the same way and that
some behaviors like joint ownership and
profit sharing may have been limited to
particular areas or economic activities.
It's an interesting discussion to be
sure. If you'd like to learn more, I
highly recommend this paper on corporate
personality in Roman private law. It's
got some great details that we haven't
had time to cover in this video.
For now, I hope we've provided you with
a good overview of the economic
landscape of antiquity. From the small
family-based operations to the networks
of societies, the collegia of
professional guilds and the private
contractors.
Clearly, there is a growing scale of
their size and sophistication.
Unfortunately, we lack the records to
precisely identify or rank them to see
which one was the biggest. Nonetheless,
we can briefly review a couple
contenders.
One area we might look would be the
agricultural sector since after all this
was still a largely agrarian era. Here
the dominant players would have been the
elite families that ran the leafundia.
These massive estates gobbled up as much
land as they could to produce industrial
quantities of commodities like olive oil
or wine. Naturally the largest of these
would have been located in the bread
baskets of the empire. Plenny, for
instance, states that just six men owned
half of Africa. It's an exaggeration to
be sure, but does give us a sense of
their great stature.
Another area where the rich accumulated
property would have been in and around
cities. In the 1st century BC, Cassus
was said to be one of the wealthiest men
in Rome. He achieved this status by
ruthlessly snapping up plots auctioned
off during the prescriptions and by
extorting owners with his private fire
brigade that would supposedly refuse to
save a home unless it was sold off for
pennies on the dollar.
Another wealthy sector would have been
maritime trade. Here there was much
money to be made shipping goods across
the Mediterranean or making voyages to
distant lands. One famous example is of
Ko the Elder who was known to be a
member of a 50-man group involved in
financing maritime activity. Together
they could have used their collective
capital to fund ship building operation
and maintenance. They may have also
worked to offer a maritime loan known as
a Punia Triticia. In these agreements,
lenders would advance money for a sea
voyage. In the event that the ship was
lost to storms or pirates, the borrower
owed nothing. Thus, to compensate for
this high risk, interest rates were
between 20 and 50%.
Taking such large cuts of such a high
volume activity must have yielded
incredible riches, especially during
years of booming trade, such as the
frenzied rush to India in the late 1st
century AD.
Others, meanwhile, got rich skimming
their profits off high-volume government
contracts like the Publicani tax
collectors or the military suppliers.
We could go on and on with speculation
of who was the leader of their
particular economic sphere. Ultimately,
however, it seems that the truly
wealthiest men were those who co-opted
the reigns of government to enrich
themselves to levels otherwise
unachievable by conventional means.
Generals like Pompy and Caesar, for
instance, wielded the Roman legions to
conquer vast swaths of land, gaining
mountains of gold, slaves, and tribute
in the process that would eclipse any of
their rivals.
Augustus eventually formalized this
system by setting up the state finances
in such a way that taxation of the
imperial provinces went directly to the
fiscus, the emperor's own chest. His
heirs would carry on this tradition
whereby the personal wealth of the
emperor was effectively the wealth of
the state. But we'll have to explore the
imperial budget another time.
For me, this discussion of ancient
businesses has been a great reminder
that while studying the wars and battles
of antiquity can be fascinating, they
ultimately had little impact on your
average person, whose experiences were
far more shaped by their interactions
with the economies that truly ruled
their world.
A big thanks to our fans on Patreon and
YouTube memberships for supporting the
channel and to the researchers, writers,
and artists for making this episode
possible. We couldn't have done it
without this team and this community. If
you enjoyed this episode, be sure to
like and subscribe for more content and
check out these other related videos.
See you in the next one.